rit.edu 2019-06-13

# Privacy Statement | Rochester Institute of Technology | RIT

### Welcome

With this information we would like to explain to you how and for which purposes we use your personal data in connection with your interactions with Rochester Institute of Technology (“RIT”) and which rights and options you may have in this respect.

### Who is responsible for your personal data?

Rochester Institute of Technology, One Lomb Memorial Drive, Rochester, New York 14623, will be the primary controller for your personal data. In addition, other RIT Global entities may control or process your personal data to the extent we are required or permitted by law to share your personal data with them for the purposes described below.

### For which purposes do we use your personal data?

Personal data and other details about you that you supply as part of the student application or registration process, as an RIT student or alumni, or that are collected by us when you use the RIT network and its affiliated websites (collectively, “Services”) are used to provide you with Services and information. You have chosen to provide us with this information and we will use that information to provide you with Services.

Furthermore, we will process your personal data as required in connection with your interactions with RIT, in particular for the following purposes:

#### Applicants and Inquiries:

  * Informing you about studies at RIT, student life, enrollment process, brochures and other promotional materials by using telephone, post and electronically, including but not limited to email, text messaging and social media posts
  * Advising you about Scholarship and Financial Aid opportunities
  * Administering your application to RIT and assigning you your University ID number
  * Assessing your eligibility to apply for studies with RIT and complying with relevant laws and regulations set by federal and state entities and other accrediting and regulatory bodies as applicable (e.g., NCAA)
  * Security purposes, including ensuring integrity and security of and controlling access to our premises, secured websites and applications websites
  * Monitoring and assessing compliance with our policies and standards

#### Students:

  * General student administration, including monitoring enrollment, facilities/classroom planning, course schedules, course assignment, grade processing and other education related activities
  * Advising you about Scholarship and Financial Aid opportunities
  * Advising you about Study Abroad and Erasmus opportunities
  * Contacting you about your billing and financial aid, including outstanding dues or overpayments
  * Career planning and development, cooperative education employment opportunities, guidance for employment opportunities, communication with your employers to ensure proper cooperative education grading
  * Academic advising to ensure proper academic guidance during your studies at RIT
  * Supporting your engagement with the RIT Community, including but not limited to your engagement with clubs and other RIT organizations
  * To evaluate and improve programs offered at RIT
  * Advising you and your families about upcoming college events, student life, Study Abroad/Erasmus opportunities (direct communication, email, social media, and via printed newsletter)
  * Providing notice and information relating to any potential academic or disciplinary actions which may be commenced against you
  * Providing health services through the Student Health Center
  * Security purposes, including ensuring integrity and security of and controlling access to our premises, IT and communication systems, platforms and secured websites and applications websites and other systems or facilities (including monitoring by camera or other means of surveillance), investigating, preventing and detecting security threats, fraud, theft or other criminal or malicious activities
  * Legal and other regulatory or compliance purposes, such as state and federal recordkeeping and other record retention obligations, NCAA compliance, etc.
  * Monitoring and assessing compliance with our policies and standards

#### Alumni:

  * General alumni networking database administration, including gathering your contact information, work place data and additional education information
  * Advising you about further education opportunities at RIT
  * Advising you about career opportunities, career planning and development
  * Advising you about Scholarship and Financial Aid opportunities
  * Contacting you about outstanding financial obligations
  * Advising you about benefits programs and other activities that are essential for Alumni Association functioning
  * Security purposes, including ensuring integrity and security of and controlling access to our premises, IT and communication systems, platforms and secured websites and applications websites and other systems or facilities (including monitoring by camera or other means of surveillance), investigating, preventing and detecting security threats, fraud, theft or other criminal or malicious activities
  * Legal and other regulatory or compliance purposes, such as archive and record keeping obligations
  * Monitoring and assessing compliance with our policies and standards

Processing is either necessary for the performance of our contract with you regarding Services, or necessary for purposes of our legitimate interest. These legitimate interests, however, do not override your interests or fundamental rights and freedoms. In addition, the processing may be based on your consent where you have expressly given that to us.

Subject to applicable law, RIT reserves the right to send you certain communications, such as service announcements, administrative messages, and other communications relating to the Services.

Where you have provided your explicit consent or as otherwise required in pursuit of a legitimate business interest of RIT, your name, email address, and contact number may be used to provide you, or permit selected third parties to provide you, with information about services we feel may interest you. You may unsubscribe from the receipt of this information.

### Which personal data do we collect?

Unless otherwise agreed to by you, we will collect only personal data which are required in connection with our relationship with you for the above purposes. This typically includes the following categories of data:

  * Personal details, such as name, address, date of birth, emergency contact details, gender, country of residence, citizenship, and tax related details if necessary
  * Information about your high school studies and previous college records including grades and information regarding any disciplinary processes
  * Degree continuation related information processed in connection with your enrollment or voluntarily provided by you, such as alternate email addresses, information about your personal and professional life, etc.
  * Identification documentation, such as copies of your passport, driving license, national or work ID card, or other documentation required by law (which may include photographs of your face)
  * Professional details where applicable or necessary to aid in your career development, such as your work contact details, position and career data, CV, details of your qualifications, relevant experience and skills
  * Data relating to access to and use of our systems, facilities and premises including data generated through monitoring by camera or other means of surveillance
  * Data relating to any travel done for RIT purposes that is considered business travel
  * Data relating to your Student Life activities (e.g., RIT club participation)
  * Data relating to your academic studies and activities at RIT (e.g., information provided during classes and courses, academic support center and related services, etc.)

### How do we collect personal data?

We will collect your personal data primarily directly from you through direct communication. However, some data may also be collected from your application(s) through online portals and social media (e.g., Facebook, Instagram, LinkedIn, etc) or from other third-parties with whom RIT contracts for services.

For further information on cookie data set or collected by RIT websites, please refer to RIT’s Cookie Statement.

### How do we protect your personal data?

RIT will maintain physical, electronic and procedural safeguards in accordance with data protection requirements to protect your personal data from unauthorized access or intrusion. These safeguards include implementing specific technologies and procedures designed to protect your privacy, such as firewalls, access controls, vulnerability scanning, threat management, application-level filtering, patching, logging, and SSL encryption. For detailed information on our data protection practices, see our Information Security Policy and Standards.

### With whom will we share your personal data?

We may share your personal data with:

  * RIT subsidiaries and affiliates if and to the extent required for legally permitted business purposes. In such cases, these subsidiaries and affiliates will use the personal data for the same purposes and under the same conditions as outlined in this Privacy Statement.
  * Third parties who process your personal data on their own behalf but in connection with a service provided to us.
  * Service providers and data processors, domestically or abroad (e.g. webmasters, Human Resources and finance database providers, student database providers, workplace safety advisors, cloud providers) instructed to process personal data for legally permitted business purposes on our behalf and in accordance with our instructions. RIT will retain control over and will remain fully responsible for your personal data and will use appropriate safeguards as required by applicable law to ensure the integrity and security of your personal data when engaging such service providers and data processors.
  * Public or governmental bodies, enforcement authorities, attorneys or courts when required to do so by applicable law, regulation or request in compliance with a legal obligation or for the establishment, exercise or defense of legal claims.
  * Third parties to whom you direct or give us permission, when we are required by applicable law, regulations or judicial or official request to do so, or when we suspect fraudulent or criminal activities.

### Your data protection rights

If you are an EU resident, you may request access to, rectification, erasure or restriction of processing of your personal data, subject to applicable EU law. You may also have the right to object to processing or request data portability and request a copy of the personal data that we hold about you.

For any of the above requests, please send a description of your personal data stating your name, your date of birth and your place of birth as proof of identity to the contact details below. We may require additional proof of identity to protect your personal data against unauthorized access. We will carefully consider your request and may discuss with you how it can best be fulfilled.

If you have given us your consent for the processing of your personal data you can withdraw the consent at any time with future effect, i.e. the withdrawal of the consent does not affect the lawfulness of processing based on the consent before its withdrawal. However, if you withdraw such consent, RIT may no longer be able to offer you all of the Services. In case consent is withdrawn, we may only further process the personal data where there is another legal ground for the processing.

If you have any concerns about how your personal data is handled by us or wish to raise a complaint, you can contact us at the contact details below to have the matter investigated. If you are not satisfied with our response or believe we are processing your personal data not in accordance with the law you can complain to the competent data protection supervisory authority in your country.

### Are you required to provide personal data?

As a general principle, you voluntarily provide us with your personal data. However, in certain circumstances we are required to collect certain personal data for legal purposes, for example because this personal data is required to be able to complete a contractual relationship, including your education or for other Services. In these cases, if you do not provide us with your personal information, we may be unable to provide you Services such as, but no limited to, administering your application/enrollment, assign certain tasks to you or permit you to participate in certain activities or services offered in connection with your studies or other interactions with RIT.

### How long do we store personal data?

If you are an EU resident, RIT will delete your personal data when it is no longer reasonably required for business purposes or you withdraw your consent (where applicable), provided that we are not legally required or otherwise permitted to continue storing such data. RIT will not delete your personal data where it may be retained for the public interest, scientific or historical research purposes or statistical purposes. Please refer to our data retention policies for further details.

### Links disclaimer

RIT’s web systems contain links to external sites run by third parties. RIT makes no warranty, expressed or implied, regarding the content or information collection practices of these sites. This Privacy Statement only applies to RIT.

### Information disclaimer

While all attempts are made to provide accurate, current, and reliable information, RIT recognizes the possibility of human and/or mechanical error. Therefore, RIT and its officers and employees make no representations as to the accuracy, completeness, or suitability of the information provided by this website, and deny any expressed or implied warranty as to the same.

### Updates to this privacy statement

This Privacy Statement was last updated in May 2018. We reserve the right to update and change this Privacy Statement from time to time in order to reflect changes in the way in which we use your personal data or for changing legal requirements. Any amended Privacy Statement will apply from the date it is posted on RIT website or otherwise made available to you.

### How to get in touch with us

If you have any questions regarding your rights or if you have any specific requests relating to your personal data please contact us at:
